Hi everyone, my name is Kathy Lau and I study computer science at Columbia University.
This summer I'm an intern at IBM.
We'll open up our discussion about Z and OS Unix shell commands
by discussing how you can learn the syntax of any shell command
and some of the code page considerations that you need to keep in mind.
Shell commands are entered either at the shell command prompt
when you're logged in directly to the shell through rlogin or telnet
or at the bottom of the screen when you're logged into the shell through tso using the omvs command.
When you're logged into the shell through tso,
the commands entered at the command line are echoed at the command prompt.
If any output is generated by the command,
it then appears on the terminal screen following the command by default.
When a command is entered, it's often followed by arguments.
The delimiters between the command and the various arguments are spaces.
At least one space is required, but you can type more than one space as a delimiter.
Anything other than spaces, however, are considered to be part of the command string itself.
And this makes sense because almost any character is valid as part of a path name
and there are many wildcard characters and meta characters that Unix can recognize.
Commands often consist of just a few characters.
For example, ls for the list command, cp for the copy command,
and pwd for print working directory command.
The format of z and os Unix shell commands
in both the command entry and command syntax diagrams
is the same as for other Unix systems.
Therefore, the os command, for example, is entered in the same way as the same syntax
except for a few options that might be different on different systems
and produce very similar results on z, os Unix, and other Unix systems.
In syntax diagrams found in manuals or produced by the main command,
brackets might appear around a list of like options.
The values that appear inside the bracket are actually optional items
and might or might not be entered.
Any arguments outside of the bracket are required and must be entered.
Speaking of documentation, the main command is the shell command which stands for manuals.
It is the Unix online hub command.
The main command displays sections from the online command reference manual
describing the command in question.
So for example, typing man space ls produces the reference manual
that describes the usage of the ls command.
The output from the main command often consists of many lines of data.
Much more of that appears on the screen.
Normally, output sent to determine the screen scrolls across the screen
until all of the output has been displayed.
But this is not the case with man.
Output from the main command is formatted and displayed one screen at a time.
Pressing the enter key displays the next line of output
while pressing the space key displays the next screen of output.
And to exit from the main output without displaying all of the screens,
simply press the Q key for quit.
When you're logged into the z-os-unix shell from TSO using the omvs command,
there are often two different code pages being used.
The default us-english z-slash-os-slash-tsocode page is cp00037
and the default z-os-unix code page is cp01047.
There are two characters which are mapped differently in these two code pages,
the left and right square brackets.
These characters are used in command syntax diagrams
and are displayed on the screen when using the main command.
These two characters are not displayed correctly when coming into the shell through TSO.
A code page for a character set determines the graphic character
produced for each hexadecimal code,
so the code page is determined by the programs and the national languages being used.
For most countries, z-os uses one code page
and the z-os-unix shell uses a different one.
To complicate the matter even further,
many users have workstations which use an ASCII-based code page.
So when moving data between these environments,
the data might have to be converted between the code pages
to maintain the same characters.
This might result in different hexadecimal codes
depending on the code pages being used.
There are code page conversion tables located in sys1.linklib
which can be used to convert between the z-os code page
and the shell code page for the national languages
supported by the z-os-unix shell.
The source for these code page tables can be found in sys1.synclib.
They can be used as samples for creating a new table
if an installation has special requirements.
The convert parameter on the omvs command
is used to set up a code page conversion table
that handles input to z-os-unix and output displayed at the terminal
in the shell environment.
The table bpxfx111 is for translation between z-os-code page IBM 037
and z-os-unix-code page IBM 1047.
This would be used by most shell users in the US.
The other example is for a conversion table
that is located in a pds named unix.linklib.
If you are accessing the shell through the rlogin or telnet interface,
automatic and correct conversion is provided.
In order to properly display the square brackets,
you must use the right code page.
Unfortunately, the dirty270mla program
cannot change the code page spontaneously,
but is easily addressed it.
Simply log off and log on again when changing code pages.
Instead of using the main command,
you can also reach this z-os-manual entry
from the unix shell by entering oh help man.
Note that the code page here is set to 0037
in the dirty270mla program,
so it fits the code page of z-os-tso-ispf.
Here the code page is set to 1047 in the dirty270mla program,
so it does not fit the code page of z-os-tso-ispf,
but does fit the code page of the unix shell.
To perform code page conversion,
we can use omvs-convert.
The format is omvs-convert parentheses data set,
parentheses member name.
If data set name is omitted,
z-os locates member name using the default search order
for modules in the system library, Kukat Nations.
The located member name is used as the character conversion table.
For example, if you specify omvs-convert bpx-fx-111,
the character conversion table is bpx-111
in the default module search order in the system library, Kukat Nations.